Bilal Ahmad



iOS App Developer

Swift | SwiftUI | UIKit



https://ibilal.netlify.app/



github.com//iBilal16



twitter.com/i_Bilal16



linkedin.com/in/bilalahmad16

I love to build tricky and complex UI's for your iOS apps. Give me visual challenges and I'll be a happy camper. I build apps that are easy to use. I've got 3+ years of experience as an iOS developer. Experienced mobile app developer with a proven track record of delivering well-received and commercially viable apps.

I program iPhone/iPad (iOS) apps with Swift. Over the years I have developed and launched many iOS apps to Apple App Store. Many of them were my own open source apps/games and many were projects for clients all over the world.

3+ years of programming and design experience. I have a keen eye on animation and that 'extra spark' that makes enjoyable apps standout.

Experiences

CryptoExpress (Bangkok, Remote)

iOS app developer

07/2022 - Present

Building iPhone and iPad apps. Business apps, Finance Crypto Currency apps, etc. Please review Projects section.

Img Advisors (Texas, Remote)

iOS app developer

03/2022 - 08/2022

HealthWiz360 is a digital fitness application for medical patients and their care team. Please review Projects section.

SAID IT (Jeddah - Pakistan , Hybrid)

iOS app developer

02/2020 - 02/2022

Striving to make the best restaurant apps, e-commerce apps, services apps (enaba), car repairing & auto parts apps, said cart app for the people who wants to buy online products, add to cart, check out, payment method, coupon and many more. Please review Projects section.

Education

University Of Engineering & Technology Peshawar, Pakistan.

Computer Software Engineering

2015 - 2019

Software Development, Programming & Data Structures, Software Quality Testing and communication studies

Edwardes College Peshawar, Pakistan.

Pre-Engineering (Engineering)

2013 - 2015

Mathematics, Chemistry, Physics, Communication Statistics.

Model School Swat, Pakistan.

High School, (Science) 2000 - 2013

Mathematics, Chemistry, Physics, Communication.

Languages

English (Full Professional), Urdu (Native or Bilingual), Pashto(Native).

Skills

iOS Development, Swift, UIKit, UX Design, Firebase Push Notifications, Interaction Design, Figma, Adobe XD, Project management, Test Flight, App Store, Postman, SDK's, Third-Party Integration, Unit Testing, Maps Integration. Consuming REST API, Codable Protocols, Payment Gateways, MVC, Core Data & Core ML, UI.xib storyboards, JSON / XML Parsing Swift UI, Adaptability.

Tools

Xcode, Sketch, Adobe XD, Figma, Apple App Store Connect, Postman, Fork (git client), Github, Transmit, Sublime Text, Slack, Skype, Firebase, Dropbox, Unity 3D, Test Flight, Visual Studio. Zoom, WPS Office, Pages.

Selection of Projects



Finansia

Senior iOS Developer

Finansia is a next generation crypto app. Finansia is basically a finance based app for crypto exchange a kind of replica for binance. It has alot of features. App also supports multiple Languages.



E-Municipality

Mid iOS Developer

Citizens can report problems, access data, track grievances and get feedback, helping to control corruption, increase openness and trust in government, and empower government. (FYP Project)



HealthWiz360

Senior iOS Developer

HealthWiz360 is an on-demand iOS app for Health & Fitness monitoring. HWiz360 app can control your diet, fitness and many more health related things. In real-time user can know about his/her diet, weight, calories. it is basically R&D based Project.



Car-Way

Mid iOS Developer

Car Way is an on-demand iOS app for Car repairing & Auto Spare parts e commerce platform. App development was done integrating/ Consuming REST API's and design was developed in UIKit from client requirements and was a really interesting challenge.



Enabatal Manasek

Mid iOS Developer

The App is a digital platform to enable muslims around the world to perform Umrah on behalf of their deceased parents, relatives, providing a reliable digital medium to the users and performers.

http://manasek.net/app_features



SweaterShop SwiftUI

Mid iOS Developer

The very first app in the Swift UI for ecommerce shop, Purely developed in SwiftUI using diffrent cards, cart functionality, animations etc.Learning based application.



Shopi Cart

Mid iOS Developer

This e-commerce app allows users to search, find, cart, add to favorite, and order products from their couch with reliable delivery partners. I worked Independently on this project.



Flash-Chat

Junior iOS Developer

Flash Chat is a beautiful and simple app for chatting as well as requesting and communication. This app supports Firebase communication & authentication, Actually it is a boot camp based open source project.



Food Cart

Mid iOS Developer

This restaurant app allows users to search, find, order and deliver food from their favorite place, set on their couch, with reliable delivery partners. It has features such as Restaurant Side, Driver Side, and Track the time of food from ordering to delivery.



See-Food

Junior iOS Developer

I have developed this app from Angela Boot camp. The idea of this app for developing came due to silicon valley season, it is basically a CoreML Based App for detecting food item, such as hot dog or not hot dog. Just for the learning purpose.